Michelle Jonika

BIOINFORMATICS · COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY · MOLECULAR GENETICS · SCIENCE COMMUNICATION

4225 Pendleton Dr. Apt. 7104 Bryan, TX, 77802, USA

🛮 (281)-825-9621 | 🗷 michellemjonika@gmail.com | 🏕 michellejonika@github.io | 🖸 michellejonika | 🛅 michellejonika

Summary.

Detail-oriented planning, project management, experimental design, and clear communication are crucial components of my critical thinking and problem-solving strategies. As a Ph.D. holder in Genetics and Genomics from Texas A&M University (Spring 2023), I currently serve as a postdoctoral research scholar. In this role, I find satisfaction in tackling the puzzle-like nature of coding genetics and genomics problems, with a particular focus on the evolution of genomic content and sex chromosomes.

Expertise

Genomics: NGS Analysis and Pipeline Development (SRA, Trimmomatic, bwa, samtools, GATK), Genome Assembly (HiFiasm,

MitoHiFi, QUAST, BUSCO), RNASeq (FastQC, bowtie2, DESeq2), GWAS (PLINK, GEMMA), Genomic Prediction (rrBLUP)

Genetics: Evolutionary Biology (Genome structure evolution, Mammalian Sex chromosome evolution, Morphometrics),

Veterinary Medicine (Clinical Data Evaluation, Cancer Prediction), Crop Science (Epistasis, Introgression)

Molecular Biology: Primer optimization, gDNA/DNA extraction, RNA extraction, PCR, qPCR, Gel visualization/imaging, Flow Cytometry

Programming: R, Linux/Unix, tidyverse, Python, LaTeX, HTML/CSS, R Shiny, Git/GitHub, VSCode, BitBucket, Docker, JIRA, conda

Data Science:Large dataset management (>20Gb), Machine Learning, Bayesian statistics, Phylogenetics, Simulations, Data Visualization, Software Development, Amazon Web Services (AWS)/Cloud Computing, HPC Cluster Computing

Project management, Public Speaking and Communication, Leadership, Multi-disciplinary Collaboration, Adaptive

problem solving, Multi-tasking, Self-Motivated, Time Management, Strategic Planning

Education

Ph.D. in Genetics and Genomics

Soft Skills:

College Station, Texas

TEXAS A&M UNIVERSITY | ADVISOR: HEATH BLACKMON

Aug. 2018 - May 2023

• Dissertation: Patterns and Processes in the Evolution of Sequence Classes and Genomic Compartments

B.S. in Forensic and Investigative Science

College Station, Texas

TEXAS A&M UNIVERSITY | ADVISOR: AARON M. TARONE

Aug. 2014 - May 2018

• Thesis: Genes as Markers of Sex for Forensic Entomology

Experience

Postdoctoral Research Scholar

College Station, Texas

TEXAS A&M DEPARTMENT OF BIOLOGY

June 2023 - Current

- · Designing an automated genomic pipeline to categorize genomic characteristics for mammalian species totaling 1000s of TB of genomic data
- Assembling and annotating highly contiguous genomes for four giant beetles of North America and other beetles of importance in conservation

PetDx San Diego, California

BIOINFORMATICS INTERN | BIOINFORMATICS TEAM

June 2022 - Aug. 2022

- Leveraged high-complexity data set to predict canine cancer types
- Used machine learning (Random Forest) approaches to train and evaluate different models
- · Performed extensive data evaluation to curate sample metrics, obtain balanced training and testing sets, and identify meaningful model parameters

Bayer Crop Science St. Louis, Missouri

GENOMICS DISCOVERY AND APPLICATION INTERN | GENETIC DISCOVERY TEAM

May 2021 - Aug. 2021

- · Identifying historic data to test for epistasis and designing a follow-up experiment to test for epistasis
- Developing a statistical testing framework to identify interactions between introgressed loci
- Three-month, full-time position exposure in an industry setting
- · Establishing multi-disciplinary connections with teams with expertise in data science, genomics, and precision breeding

Ph.D. Researcher College Station, Texas

TEXAS A&M INTERDISCIPLINARY PROGRAM IN GENETICS AND GENOMICS | TEXAS A&M DEPARTMENT OF BIOLOGY

Aug. 2018 - May 2023

- Developing an R package (Lo et al. 2019) to characterize microsatellite evolution and applying this package to characterize microsatellite evolution across 300 million years of insect evolution (Jonika et al. 2020)
- Elucidating the role of centromere type in insect chromosome number evolution (Ruckman et al. 2020) and effective population size in carnivore and beetle chromosome number evolution (Jonika et al. Accepted with Minor Revision; Blackmon et al. 2024)
- Detail perspectives on the rarity of univalent sex chromosome systems across the tree of life (Jonika et al. 2022)

March 11, 2024 Michelle Jonika · Résumé 1

Teaching & Mentorship

Teaching Assistant

DEPARTMENT OF BIOLOGY | DEPARTMENT OF GENETICS

- Python for Biologists | Spring 2023 | Texas A&M
- Anatomy and Physiology | Spring 2022 | Texas A&M
- Critical Writing in Biology | Fall 2020, Spring 2021 | Texas A&M
- Introduction to Genetics Laboratory | Spring 2019, Spring 2023 | Texas A&M
- Guest Lecture Forensic Genetics | Topic: Genetic Testing | Fall 2022, Fall 2023 | Texas A&M
- Guest Lecture Bioinformatics | Topic: Genetic Privacy | Fall 2021 | Utah Valley University
- Guest Lecture Forensic Entomology | Topic: Genetics and Insect Development | Spring 2023 | Texas A&M

Leadership & Outreach

Texas A&M College of Science

OUTREACH COMMITTEE | WOMEN IN SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

Jan. 2019 - Current

- Participated in various outreach activities important to the mission of the College of Science and Women in Science and Engineering
- · Served on the Women in Science and Engineering outreach committee and organized school STEM nights

Genetics Graduate Student Association

PRESIDENT | VICE PRESIDENT | GRADUATE STUDENT REPRESENTATIVE | SEMINAR COMMITTEE

May 2019 - May 2023

- Facilitate monthly graduate student association meetings
- · Oversee communication between current graduate students, genetics faculty, and the program executive committee

Genetics Society of America

EARLY CAREER LEADERSHIP PROGRAM - CAREER DEVELOPMENT SUBCOMMITTEE

Jan. 2020 - Dec. 2022

- Contribute career development blog pieces for Genes to Genomes blog
- Curate resources contributing to a career development toolkit and early career researcher newsletters
- Organize career development workshops for bimonthly workshop series and TAGC conference

Recent Awards

- 2023 Texas A&M Distinguished Graduate Student Award, Texas A&M University
- 2023 Montgomery Award, Texas A&M University Graduate and Professional School
- 2023 Outstanding Ph.D. Student Presentation, Biology Department, Student PostDoc Research Conference
- 2022 Texas A&M Data Science Ambassador, Texas A&M University
- 2022 **Research Excellence Award**, Interdisciplinary Genetics and Genomics Program

Selected Publications

*Please see Google Scholar for a full publications list

T. Sylvester, Z. Hoover, C.E. Hjelmen, M.M. Jonika, et al. A Reference Quality Genome Assembly for the Jewel Scarab Chrysina gloriosa. – Accepted

M.M. Jonika, A. Arekere, K. Wilhoit, H. Blackmon. Small Effective Population Size Drives Chromosome Number Evolution in Carnivores. – Accepted

H. Blackmon, **M.M. Jonika**, J.M. Alfieri, J.P. Demuth. 2024. Assessing the Impact of Key Ecological and Phenotypic Transitions on the Rate of Karyotype Evolution: Drift Drives the Evolution of Chromosome Number. – *In Print*

J.M. Alfieri, M.M. Jonika, J.N. Dulin, H. Blackmon. 2023. Tempo and Mode of Genome Structure Evolution in Insects. Genes. – 14(2): 336.

M. Pitonak, M. Aceves, P.A. Kumar, G. Dampf, P. Green, A. Tucker, V. Dietz, D. Miranda, S. Letchuman, **M.M. Jonika**, D. Bautista, H. Blackmon, J.N. Dulin. 2022. Effects of Biological Sex Mismatch on Neural ProgenitorCell Transplantation for Spinal Cord Injury in Mice. Nature Communications. 13(1):1-12.

M.M. Jonika, J.M. Alfieri, T. Sylvester, A.R. Buhrow, H. Blackmon. 2022. Why Not Y Naught. Heredity. 129. 75-78.

J.M. Alfieri, G. Wang, M.M. Jonika, C.A. Gill, G.N. Athrey, H. Blackmon. 2022. A Primer for Single-Cell Sequencing in Non-Model Organisms. Genes 13(2).

M.L. Pimsler, C.E. Hjelmen, **M.M. Jonika**, A. Sharma, S. Fu, M. Bala, S.H. Sze, J.K. Tomberlin, A.M.Tarone. 2021. Sexual Dimorphism in Growth Rate and Gene Expression Throughout Immature Development in Wild Type Chrysomya rufifacies (Diptera: Calliphoridae) Macquart. Frontiers in Ecology and Evolution 9: 368.

S. Ruckman*(Co-first author), M.M. Jonika*(Co-first author), C. Casola, H. Blackmon. 2020. Chromosome Number Evolves at Equal Rates in Holocentric and Monocentric Clades. PLOS Genetics 16(10):e1009076.

M.M. Jonika, J. Lo, H. Blackmon. 2020. Mode and Tempo of Microsatellite Evolution across 300 Million Years of Insect Evolution. Genes 11:945.

M.M. Jonika, C.E. Hjelmen, A.M. Faris, A.S. McGuane A.M. Tarone. 2020. An Evaluation of Differentially Spliced Genes as Markers of Sex for Forensic Entomology. J. of Forensic Science 65(5): 1579-1587

J. Lo, M.M. Jonika, H. Blackmon. 2019. micRocounter: Microsatellite Characterization in Genome Assemblies. G3 9(10): 3101-3104